I wrote a letter last week talking about the work of the foundation,
في الأسبوع المنصرم كتبت رسالة عن عمل المؤسسة
sharing some of the problems.
باثّاً فيها بعض الإشكاليات
And Warren Buffet had recommended I do that --
وقد طلب مني وارن بافِت ذلك
being honest about what was going well, what wasn't,
بأن أكون أميناً في عرض الإيجابيات والسلبيات
and making it kind of an annual thing.
وأن يكون هذا نوعاً من الواجب السنوي
A goal I had there was to draw more people in to work on those problems,
وهدفي من هذا هو جذب المزيد من الأشخاص لحل تلك المشاكل
because I think there are some very important problems
لأنني أعتقد بأن هناك بعض المشاكل شديدة الأهمية
that don't get worked on naturally.
ومع ذلك لم تُعامل بالشكل المطلوب
That is, the market does not drive the scientists,
بمعنى أن المجال لا يحمس العلماء
the communicators, the thinkers, the governments
ولا المتحدثين, أو المفكرين, أو الحكومات
to do the right things.
للقيام بالأعمال المطلوبة
And only by paying attention to these things
ومن خلال الاهتمام بهذه المشاكل
and having brilliant people who care and draw other people in
وبوجود أناس مهتمين أذكياء وبدفع الآخرين إليها
can we make as much progress as we need to.
فسنتمكن من إحراز قدراً كبيراً من التقدم الذي ننشده
So this morning I'm going to share two of these problems
لذا سنتناقش في هذا الصباح حول اثنتين من تلك المشاكل
and talk about where they stand.
وسنتحدث عن وضعهما
But before I dive into those I want to admit that I am an optimist.
وقبل الغوص فيهما أريد أن أعترف بأنني متفائل
Any tough problem, I think it can be solved.
لأن أي مشكلة صعبة بالإمكان حلها
And part of the reason I feel that way is looking at the past.
وجزء من سبب هذا الشعور هو النظر إلى الماضي
Over the past century, average lifespan has more than doubled.
فخلال القرن الماضي, بلغ متوسط العمر أكثر من الضعف
Another statistic, perhaps my favorite,
الإحصائية الأخرى, ربما هي ما أُفضّل
is to look at childhood deaths.
هي أن ننظر في وفيات الأطفال
As recently as 1960, 110 million children were born,
فإلى عهد قريب وفي عام 1960, ولد 110 ملايين طفلاً
and 20 million of those died before the age of five.
ومات منهم 20 مليوناً قبل سن الخامسة
Five years ago, 135 million children were born -- so, more --
أما قبل خمس سنين, فبلغ عدد المواليد 135 مليوناً - أي أنه أكثر-
and less than 10 million of them died before the age of five.
ومات منهم قبل الخامسة أقل من 10 ملايين
So that's a factor of two reduction of the childhood death rate.
وهذا عامل انخفاضين في معدل وفيات الأطفال
It's a phenomenal thing.
وهو أمر هائل
Each one of those lives matters a lot.
فحياة كل واحد منهم تهم كثيرا
And the key reason we were able to it was not only rising incomes
والسبب الرئيسي في تمكننا من ذلك لم يكن فقط ارتفاع مستوى الدخل
but also a few key breakthroughs:
وإنما بعض الاكتشافات المهمة
vaccines that were used more widely.
كاللقاحات التي استخدمت على نطاق واسع
For example, measles was four million of the deaths
فعلى سبيل المثال, تسبب مرض الحصبة في وفاة أربعة ملايين
back as recently as 1990
وذلك إلى عهد قريب في عام 1990
and now is under 400,000.
والآن انخفضت إلى أقل من 400.000
So we really can make changes.
وبالتالي فإنه يمكننا إحداث تغييرات
The next breakthrough is to cut that 10 million in half again.
التطور القادم هو خفض تلك العشرة ملايين إلى النصف مرة أخرى
And I think that's doable in well under 20 years.
وأعتقد بأنه يمكن تحقيق ذلك في أقل من 20 سنة
Why? Well there's only a few diseases
أما لماذا؟ فلأن هناك عدد قليل من الأمراض
that account for the vast majority of those deaths:
التي تشكل الغالبية العظمى لهذه الوفيات
diarrhea, pneumonia and malaria.
كالإسهال, والملاريا, والالتهاب الرئوي
So that brings us to the first problem that I'll raise this morning,
وهذا يوصلنا إلى المشكلة الأولى التي سأثيرها هذا الصباح
which is how do we stop a deadly disease that's spread by mosquitos?
والتي تتعلق بكيفية إيقاف ذلك المرض القاتل الذي ينتشر عن طريق البعوض؟
Well, what's the history of this disease?
حسناً, ماهو تاريخ هذا المرض؟
It's been a severe disease for thousands of years.
لقد ظل مرضاً مرعباً منذ آلاف السنين
In fact, if we look at the genetic code,
وفي الحقيقة, إذا كان لنا أن ننظر في الشفرة الوراثية
it's the only disease we can see
فإنه يمكننا أن نرى بأنه المرض الوحيد
that people who lived in Africa
الذي قام سكان أفريقيا
actually evolved several things to avoid malarial deaths.
بتطوير الكثير من الأشياء لتجنب وفيات الملاريا
Deaths actually peaked at a bit over five million in the 1930s.
وبلغت الوفيات ذروتها عندما تجاوزت الخمسة ملايين بقليل في الثلاثينات
So it was absolutely gigantic.
وبالتالي أعتبر وباء
And the disease was all over the world.
وانتشر المرض في كافة أرجاء المعمورة
A terrible disease. It was in the United States. It was in Europe.
مرض مرعب. وصل إلى الى الولايات المتحدة الأمريكية. وأوروبا
People didn't know what caused it until the early 1900s,
ولم يتعرف الناس على مسبباته حتى أوائل عام 1900
when a British military man figured out that it was mosquitos.
عندما اكتشف رجل تابع للجيش البريطاني بأنه البعوض
So it was everywhere.
لذا انتشر في كل مكان
And two tools helped bring the death rate down.
وساعدت أداتان في خفض معدل الوفيات
One was killing the mosquitos with DDT.
الأولى كانت قتل البعوض بالـ DDT
The other was treating the patients with quinine, or quinine derivatives.
أما الثانية فكانت معالجة المرضى باستخدام الكواينين, أو مشتقاته
And so that's why the death rate did come down.
وهذان هما سببا خفض معدل الوفيات
Now, ironically, what happened was
العجيب اليوم, أن ما حدث هو
it was eliminated from all the temperate zones,
إزالته من جميع المناطق المعتدلة
which is where the rich countries are.
والتي هي أماكن البلدان الغنية
So we can see: 1900, it's everywhere.
حتى أنه يمكننا ملاحظة تواجده في كل مكان, عام 1900
1945, it's still most places.
وفي عام 1945 كان ما يزال موجوداً في أغلب الأماكن
1970, the U.S. and most of Europe have gotten rid of it.
أما عام 1970 فقد تخلصت منه الولايات المتحدة وأغلب أوروبا
1990, you've gotten most of the northern areas.
وفي عام 1990انضمت لهم أغلب المناطق الشمالية
And more recently you can see it's just around the equator.
أما مؤخراً فترون أنه منحصر بالقرب من خط الإستواء
And so this leads to the paradox that
وهذا يقودنا إلى المفارقة التالية وهي
because the disease is only in the poorer countries,
أن انحصار المرض في البلدان الفقيرة
it doesn't get much investment.
سبّب عدم حصوله على الكثير من الاستثمارات
For example, there's more money put into baldness drugs
فعلى سبيل المثال, الأموال التي تنفق على أدوية الصلع
than are put into malaria.
أكثر من تلك المبذولة للملاريا
Now, baldness, it's a terrible thing.
فالصلع, اليوم, يعد مرضاً مرعباً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And rich men are afflicted.
ويعاني منه الأثرياء
And so that's why that priority has been set.
وهذا هو سبب حصوله على تلك الأولوية
But, malaria --
لكن, الملاريا
even the million deaths a year caused by malaria
التي تتسبب في وفاة الملايين سنوياً
greatly understate its impact.
يهمش تأثيرها
Over 200 million people at any one time are suffering from it.
فأكثر من 200 مليون شخص يعاني منها في كل لحظة
It means that you can't get the economies in these areas going
وهذا يعني أنه لا يمكنك الحصول على الكثير من الاقتصاديات في هذه المجالات
because it just holds things back so much.
بسبب احتوائها على العديد من التعقيدات
Now, malaria is of course transmitted by mosquitos.
طبعاً, الملاريا تنقلها البعوض
I brought some here, just so you could experience this.
وقد أحضرت بعضاً منها هنا, فقط لكي تستطيعوا تجربتها
We'll let those roam around the auditorium a little bit.
سأسمح لها أن تطوف قليلاً حول القاعة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
There's no reason only poor people should have the experience.
لا يوجد سبب يحصر التجربة على الفقراء فقط
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
Those mosquitos are not infected.
هذه البعوض ليست موبؤة
So we've come up with a few new things. We've got bed nets.
وقد ابتكرنا بعض الحلول الجديدة. حيث توصلنا للناموسيات -أسرة مغطاة بشبكة-
And bed nets are a great tool.
وهذه الناموسيات وسيلة رائعة
What it means is the mother and child stay under the bed net at night,
وهذا يعني أن الأم والطفل يبقون تحت تلك الناموسيات ليلاً
so the mosquitos that bite late at night can't get at them.
وبالتالي فإن البعوض الذي يلدغ في ساعات متأخرة من الليل لن يصل إليهم
And when you use indoor spraying with DDT
وعندما ترش الـ DDT داخل البيت
and those nets
بالإضافة إلى الناموسيات
you can cut deaths by over 50 percent.
فستتمكن من خفض نسبة الوفيات بنسبة تتجاوز الـ 50%
And that's happened now in a number of countries.
وهذا يحدث اليوم في عدد من الدول
It's great to see.
ومن الروعة أن نرى ذلك
But we have to be careful because malaria --
و لكن يجب علينا أن نكون حذرين من الملاريا
the parasite evolves and the mosquito evolves.
لأن الطفيليات تتطور, والبعوض يتطور كذلك
So every tool that we've ever had in the past has eventually become ineffective.
وبالتالي فكل وسيلة استخدمناها في الماضي ستصبح غير مجدية في النهاية
And so you end up with two choices.
وبذلك ينتهي بنا الأمر إلى خيارين
If you go into a country with the right tools and the right way,
فإما أن تذهب إلى دولة ومعك الأدوات الصحيحة والأسلوب السليم
you do it vigorously,
وتفعّله بقوة
you can actually get a local eradication.
مما يجعلك تستأصله محلياً
And that's where we saw the malaria map shrinking.
وهذا ما نراه على خريطة إنكماش الملاريا
Or, if you go in kind of half-heartedly,
أو أن تسير في نوع من الفتور
for a period of time you'll reduce the disease burden,
وبهذا ستقلل من عبء المرض مؤقتاً
but eventually those tools will become ineffective,
لكن في النهاية ستصبح تلك الأدوات عديمة الجدوى
and the death rate will soar back up again.
وسيعاود معدل الوفيات في الارتفاع مرة أخرى
And the world has gone through this where it paid attention and then didn't pay attention.
والعالم مرّ بهذه حيث اعتنى ثم فتر
Now we're on the upswing.
نحن اليوم على قدم وساق
Bed net funding is up.
فتمويل الناموسيات مرتفع
There's new drug discovery going on.
وهناك دواء جديد يجري تصنيعه
Our foundation has backed a vaccine that's going into phase three trial
كما أن مؤسستنا دعمت لقاحاً يسير في المرحلة الثالثة من تجربته
that starts in a couple months.
التي ابتدأت منذ شهرين
And that should save over two thirds of the lives if it's effective.
وسيحافظ ذلك على حياة أكثر من الثلثين أن نجح
So we're going to have these new tools.
لذا فإننا نمتلك أدوات جديدة
But that alone doesn't give us the road map.
لكن ذلك وحده لا يقدم لنا خارطة الطريق
Because the road map to get rid of this disease
لأن خارطة الطريق للتخلص من هذا المرض
involves many things.
يتطلب الكثير من الأمور
It involves communicators to keep the funding high,
فهي تتطلب متحدثين يساعدون على زيادة التمويل
to keep the visibility high,
ويحافظون على وضوح الرؤية
to tell the success stories.
ولكي يتحدثوا عن قصص النجاح
It involves social scientists,
وهي تتطلب علماء اجتماع
so we know how to get not just 70 percent of the people to use the bed nets,
لنعرف كيف نحصل على مستخدمي ناموسيات ليس بنسبة 70%
but 90 percent.
وإنما بنسبة 90%
We need mathematicians to come in and simulate this,
كذلك نحن بحاجة إلى علماء رياضيات ليأتوا ويحسبوا كل هذا
to do Monte Carlo things to understand how these tools combine and work together.
ويستخدموا طرق Monte Carlo لنفهم كيفية دمج هذه الأدوات لتعمل سوياً
Of course we need drug companies to give us their expertise.
كما أننا بالطبع بحاجة لشركات الأدوية لتعطينا من خبراتها
We need rich-world governments to be very generous in providing aid for these things.
ونحتاج من الحكومات الغنية أن تكون سخية جداً في تقديم المساعدات لهذه الأشياء
And so as these elements come together,
وبالتالي إذا تمكنا من جمع كل هذه العناصر
I'm quite optimistic
فكلي تفاؤل
that we will be able to eradicate malaria.
بأننا سنتمكن من القضاء على الملاريا
Now let me turn to a second question,
والآن, اسمحوا لي أن أنتقل إلى السؤال الثاني
a fairly different question, but I'd say equally important.
وهو سؤال مختلف قليلاً, لكن يمكنني القول أنه بنفس القدر من الأهمية
And this is: How do you make a teacher great?
ألا وهو: كيف تجعل المعلم عظيماً؟
It seems like the kind of question that people would spend a lot of time on,
ويبدو أنه من الأسئلة التي ينبغي على الناس بذل المزيد من الوقت فيها
and we'd understand very well.
لكي نفهمها جيداً
And the answer is, really, that we don't.
والجواب هو, أننا في الحقيقة لا نقوم بذلك
Let's start with why this is important.
دعونا نبدأ باستعراض أهميته
Well, all of us here, I'll bet, had some great teachers.
حسناً, كل الموجودين هنا, أراهن بأنه مرّ علينا معلمين عظماء
We all had a wonderful education.
وكلنا تلقينا تعليماً رائعاً
That's part of the reason we're here today,
وهذا جزء من سبب تواجدنا اليوم هنا
part of the reason we're successful.
وهو جزء من كوننا ناجحين
I can say that, even though I'm a college drop-out.
يمكنني القول, رغم انسحابي من الكلية
I had great teachers.
بأنني قابلت معلمين عظماء
In fact, in the United States, the teaching system has worked fairly well.
وفي الحقيقة, ففي الولايات المتحدة, يعمل نظام التعليم بشكل جيد
There are fairly effective teachers in a narrow set of places.
فهناك مجموعة من المعلمين الأكفاء الذين يتواجدون في قليل من الأماكن
So the top 20 percent of students have gotten a good education.
لذلك تجد أفضل 20% من الطلاب تلقوا تعليماً جيداً
And those top 20 percent have been the best in the world,
وهؤلاء الـ 20% هم الأفضل في العالم
if you measure them against the other top 20 percent.
إذا ما قارنتهم بالـ 20% الذين يلونهم في الأفضلية
And they've gone on to create the revolutions in software and biotechnology
فهم الذين يحدثون الثورات في مجال البرمجيات و التكنولوجيا الحيوية
and keep the U.S. at the forefront.
وهم من يحافظ على بقاء الولايات المتحدة في الطليعة
Now, the strength for those top 20 percent
أما اليوم, فإن قوة تلك الـ 20%
is starting to fade on a relative basis,
بدأت في التلاشي بشكل نسبي
but even more concerning is the education that the balance of people are getting.
لكن الأكثر إقلاقاً هو التعليم الذي يتلقاه الناس العاديون
Not only has that been weak. it's getting weaker.
فهو لا يعد ضعيفاً فقط؛ وإنما يزداد ضعفاً
And if you look at the economy, it really is only providing opportunities now
ولو نظرتم إلى الاقتصاد, فتجدونه يقدم في الواقع فرصاً
to people with a better education.
لمن يمتلكون تعليماً متميزاً
And we have to change this.
لذا علينا أن نغير هذا
We have to change it so that people have equal opportunity.
علينا أن نغيره حتى يحصل الجميع على فرص متساوية
We have to change it so that the country is strong
علينا أن نغيره حتى يظل البلد قوياً
and stays at the forefront
ويبقى في طليعة
of things that are driven by advanced education,
الأمور التي يقودها التعليم المتقدم
like science and mathematics.
كالعلوم والرياضيات
When I first learned the statistics,
عندما علمت عن الإحصاءات لأول مرة
I was pretty stunned at how bad things are.
صعقت من مدى سوء الأمور
Over 30 percent of kids never finish high school.
فأكثر من 30% من الأطفال لا يكملون تعليمهم الثانوي
And that had been covered up for a long time
وهو الأمر الذي أُخفي لمدة طويلة
because they always took the dropout rate as the number
لأنهم دائماً يحسبون معدل المنسحبين من خلال مقارنة عدد
who started in senior year and compared it to the number who finished senior year.
أولئك الذين بدأوا السنة الرابعة الثانوية بمن تخرجوا منها
Because they weren't tracking where the kids were before that.
بينما لا يتتبعون من هم قبل ذلك من الطلاب
But most of the dropouts had taken place before that.
حيث أن معظم الانسحابات تحدث قبل تلك السنة
They had to raise the stated dropout rate
وسيضطرون لرفع معدل المنسحبين المذكور
as soon as that tracking was done
بمجرد حدوث عملية المراقبة
to over 30 percent.
إلى أكثر من 30%
For minority kids, it's over 50 percent.
بالنسبة لأطفال الأقليات, فسيزيد عن 50%
And even if you graduate from high school,
وحتى إن تخرجت من الثانوية
if you're low-income,
وأنت من ذوي الدخل المحدود
you have less than a 25 percent chance of ever completing a college degree.
فإن فرصتك أقل من 25% مقارنة بمن أكمل تعليمه الجامعي
If you're low-income in the United States,
وإذا كنت من ذوي الدخل المنخفض في الولايات المتحدة,
you have a higher chance of going to jail
فإن فرصة دخولك السجن أكبر
than you do of getting a four-year degree.
من فرصة حصولك على الشهادة الجامعية
And that doesn't seem entirely fair.
وهو ما لايعد أمراً جيداً أبداً
So, how do you make education better?
لذلك, كيف نجعل التعليم أفضل؟
Now, our foundation, for the last nine years, has invested in this.
حالياً, فإن مؤسستنا, ومنذ تسع سنين, تقوم بالاستثمار في هذا المجال
There's many people working on it.
وهناك الكثير من العاملين على هذا.
We've worked on small schools,
لقد عملنا على المدارس الصغيرة.
we've funded scholarships,
فمولنا المنح الدراسية
we've done things in libraries.
وقمنا بالعمل لصالح المكتبات
A lot of these things had a good effect.
والكثير من هذه الأمور كان أثرها طيباً
But the more we looked at it, the more we realized that having great teachers
لكن كلما دققنا فيها أكثر, أدركنا أن وجود معلمين عظماء
was the very key thing.
هو حجر الزاوية
And we hooked up with some people studying
ولقد تواصلنا مع أشخاص يدرسون
how much variation is there between teachers,
مدى التفاوت بين المعلمين
between, say, the top quartile -- the very best --
بين, لنقل, الربع الأعلى -الأميز-
and the bottom quartile.
والربع الأدنى
How much variation is there within a school or between schools?
وعن مدى التفاوت داخل المدرسة أو بين المدارس؟
And the answer is that these variations are absolutely unbelievable.
والنتيجة هي أن ذلك التباين لايمكن تصديقه أبداً
A top quartile teacher will increase the performance of their class --
فالمعلم من فئة الربع الأعلى سيزيد من أداء فصله
based on test scores --
- طبقاً لدرجات الاختبار -
by over 10 percent in a single year.
بما يتجاوز الـ 10% في السنة الواحدة.
What does that mean?
ماذا يعني هذا؟
That means that if the entire U.S., for two years,
هذا يعني أنه إذا كانت الولايات المتحدة بأسرها, ولمدة سنتين,
had top quartile teachers,
فيها معلمين من فئة الربع الأعلى
the entire difference between us and Asia would go away.
فكل الفروقات بيننا وبين آسيا سيختفي.
Within four years we would be blowing everyone in the world away.
وفي غضون أربع سنين سنعصف بالعالم.
So, it's simple. All you need are those top quartile teachers.
وبالتالي, فالأمر بسيط, فكل ما نحتاجه هو معلمين من الربع الأعلى.
And so you'd say, "Wow, we should reward those people.
وبالتالي سوف تقول, " واو, ينبغي أن نكافئهم.
We should retain those people.
وأن نحافظ عليهم.
We should find out what they're doing and transfer that skill to other people."
وأن نكتشف ما الذي يفعلونه لننقل مهاراتهم إلى الآخرين."
But I can tell you that absolutely is not happening today.
لكن بوسعي أن أقول لكم أن هذا لا يحدث اليوم مطلقاً.
What are the characteristics of this top quartile?
ما هي مميزات فئة الربع الأعلى؟
What do they look like?
وكيف يبدون؟
You might think these must be very senior teachers.
ربما تظنون بأنهم مدرسون كبار.
And the answer is no.
والجواب هو لا.
Once somebody has taught for three years
فبمجرد أن يقوم شخص بالتدريس لثلاث سنين
their teaching quality does not change thereafter.
فإن نوعية تدريسه لا تتغير بعد ذلك.
The variation is very, very small.
فالفرق ضئيل جداً جداً.
You might think these are people with master's degrees.
وربما تظنون بأنهم من حملة الماجستير.
They've gone back and they've gotten their Master's of Education.
أي أنهم عادوا وتحصلوا على الماجستير.
This chart takes four different factors
هذا الرسم البياني يناقش أربعة عوامل مختلفة.
and says how much do they explain teaching quality.
ويبين مدى أثرها في جودة التعليم.
That bottom thing, which says there's no effect at all,
ذلك العامل الموجود في القاع, والذي يدل على أنه لا يؤثر أبداً,
is a master's degree.
هو درجة الماجستير.
Now, the way the pay system works is there's two things that are rewarded.
إن نظام الدفع ينص على أن هناك أمرين يستحقان المكافأة.
One is seniority.
الأول هو الأقدمية.
Because your pay goes up and you vest into your pension.
حيث أن راتبك يزيد, بينما تستثمر لتقاعدك.
The second is giving extra money to people who get their master's degree.
الأمر الثاني هو منح المزيد من المال للحاصلين على درجة الماجستير.
But it in no way is associated with being a better teacher.
لكنه لايهتم أبداً بمدى كونك معلماً متميزاً.
Teach for America: slight effect.
أما أن تعلم من أجل أمريكا: فأثره طفيف.
For math teachers majoring in math there's a measurable effect.
بالنسبة لمعلمي الرياضيات المتخصصين في الرياضيات هناك قياس للأثر.
But, overwhelmingly, it's your past performance.
لكن, في الأغلب, الأهمية لمستوى أدائك في الماضي.
There are some people who are very good at this.
هناك بعض المدرسين المتميزين.
And we've done almost nothing
ونحن لم نعمل تقريباً أي شيء
to study what that is
لدراسة وضعهم
and to draw it in and to replicate it,
من أجل معرفته وإعادة تكراره,
to raise the average capability --
لكي نرفع معدل القدرة
or to encourage the people with it to stay in the system.
أو لكي نشجعهم على المواصلة في هذا الميدان.
You might say, "Do the good teachers stay and the bad teacher's leave?"
ربما تقولون: "هل المعلمون الجيدون يبقون بينما يغادر السيئون؟"
The answer is, on average, the slightly better teachers leave the system.
الجواب هو, لا في المتوسط, فالمعلمون المتميزون مع قلتهم يغادرون الميدان.
And it's a system with very high turnover.
ليظل نظاماً مقلوباً بقوة.
Now, there are a few places -- very few -- where great teachers are being made.
هناك أماكن قليلة - قليلة جداً - تُعد مدرسين عظماء.
A good example of one is a set of charter schools called KIPP.
وخير مثال لأحدها هي مجموعة مدارس تسمى KIPP.
KIPP means Knowledge Is Power.
KIPP تعنى (Knowledge Is Power) المعرفة قوة.
It's an unbelievable thing.
إنه عمل مذهل.
They have 66 schools -- mostly middle schools, some high schools --
لديهم 66 مدرسة - غالبيتها للمتوسطة, وبعضها للثانوية -
and what goes on is great teaching.
وما يجري هناك يعتبر تعليماً متميزاً.
They take the poorest kids,
هم يأخذون الأطفال الأكثر فقراً,
and over 96 percent of their high school graduates go to four-year colleges.
وأكثر من 96% من خريجي الثانوية لديهم يلتحقون بالجامعة.
And the whole spirit and attitude in those schools
بينما الروح والموقف في هذه المدارس
is very different than in the normal public schools.
يختلف كلياً عن المدارس العامة العادية.
They're team teaching. They're constantly improving their teachers.
فهم فريق تدريس. ويطورون مدرسيهم باستمرار.
They're taking data, the test scores,
بأخذ البيانات, ودرجات الاختبار,
and saying to a teacher, "Hey, you caused this amount of increase."
ثم يقولون للمعلم, " أنت, يا هذا, ساهمت في هذا القدر من التحسن."
They're deeply engaged in making teaching better.
وهم منغمسين بشدة في جعل التعليم أفضل.
When you actually go and sit in one of these classrooms,
وفي الواقع, عندما تذهب وتجلس في أحد تلك الفصول,
at first it's very bizarre.
في أول الأمر تبدو في غاية الغرابة.
I sat down and I thought, "What is going on?"
جلستُ وفكرت, " ما الذي يجري؟"
The teacher was running around, and the energy level was high.
المعلم يركض, ومستوى الطاقة مرتفعاً.
I thought, "I'm in the sports rally or something.
فكرت , " هل أنا في مسابقة رياضية أو شيء من هذا.
What's going on?"
ما الذي يجري؟"
And the teacher was constantly scanning to see which kids weren't paying attention,
والمعلم كان يتفحص باستمرار ليرى مَن مِـن الطلاب لا يبدو مركزاً,
which kids were bored,
وأيهم يشعر بالملل,
and calling kids rapidly, putting things up on the board.
وينادي الطلاب بشكل سريع, ويضع الأشياء على السبورة.
It was a very dynamic environment,
إنها بيئة مفعمة بالنشاط,
because particularly in those middle school years -- fifth through eighth grade --
لأن في هذه المدارس المتوسطة خصيصاً - من السنة الخامسة إلى السنة الثامنة --
keeping people engaged and setting the tone
تُـشرك الجميع وتضع نغمة
that everybody in the classroom needs to pay attention,
أن كل واحد في الفصل ينبغي أن ينتبه,
nobody gets to make fun of it or have the position of the kid who doesn't want to be there.
ولا يسمح لأحد أن يسخر أو أن يكون في دور عدم الراغب في التواجد.
Everybody needs to be involved.
الجميع يلزمه المشاركة.
And so KIPP is doing it.
وهو ما تفعله KIPP.
How does that compare to a normal school?
كيف نقارن هذا بمدرسة عادية؟
Well, in a normal school, teachers aren't told how good they are.
حسناً, في المدارس العادية لا يخبرون بمدى إجادتهم.
The data isn't gathered.
فالبيانات لا تجمع.
In the teacher's contract,
بل إن العقد المبرم مع المعلمين,
it will limit the number of times the principal can come into the classroom --
يقيد عدد مرات الزيارة التي يقوم بها المدير للفصل --
sometimes to once per year.
تقيد أحياناً بمرة في السنة.
And they need advanced notice to do that.
ولابد من إبلاغ سابق بموعد تلك الزيارة.
So imagine running a factory where you've got these workers,
تخيل أنك تمتلك مصنعاُ ولديك أمثال أولئك العمال,
some of them just making crap
والبعض يلهو
and the management is told, "Hey, you can only come down here once a year,
ثم يخبر المدير, " أنت, يا هذا, بإمكانك المجيء هنا مرة واحدة في السنة,
but you need to let us know, because we might actually fool you,
ولابد من إخبارنا بذلك, لأننا في الواقع ربما نريد أن نخدعك,
and try and do a good job in that one brief moment."
بأن نعمل جيداً في تلك اللحظة الوحيدة القصيرة."
Even a teacher who wants to improve doesn't have the tools to do it.
بل حتى أن المعلم الجيد الباحث عن التطوير لايجد الأدوات لفعل ذلك.
They don't have the test scores,
فلا توفر لدرجات الاختبار,
and there's a whole thing of trying to block the data.
وكل الأمور تسير في محاولة حجب البيانات.
For example, New York passed a law
فعلى سبيل المثال, في نيويورك أجيز قانوناً
that said that the teacher improvement data could not be made available and used
يقول بأن بيانات تطور المعلم لا يمكن توفيرها أو استخدامها
in the tenure decision for the teachers.
ضمن حق القرارات المتاحة للمعلمين.
And so that's sort of working in the opposite direction.
وهذا النوع من العمل يسير في الاتجاه المعاكس.
But I'm optimistic about this,
لكنني متفائل إزاء هذا,
I think there are some clear things we can do.
واعتقد بأن هناك بعض الأمور الواضحة التي يمكن فعلها.
First of all, there's a lot more testing going on,
أولاً وقبل كل شيء, هناك الكثير من الاختبارات المستمرة,
and that's given us the picture of where we are.
وهذا يعطينا دلالة على وضعنا.
And that allows us to understand who's doing it well,
ويسمح لنا بمعرفة من يعمل بشكل جيد,
and call them out, and find out what those techniques are.
لدعوتهم, لنتعرف على تقنياتهم.
Of course, digital video is cheap now.
وكما تعلمون, فالفيديو الرقمي رخيص اليوم.
Putting a few cameras in the classroom
فلو وضع القليل من الكاميرات في الفصول
and saying that things are being recorded on an ongoing basis
ونُبه على أن كل الأمور تسجل بشكل مستمر
is very practical in all public schools.
فهذا يعتبر عملياً جداً لكافة المدارس الحكومية.
And so every few weeks teachers could sit down
ثم بعد كل بضعة أسابيع يجلس المعلمون
and say, "OK, here's a little clip of something I thought I did well.
ويقولون, " حسناً, هنا مقطع أظن أنني كنت رائعاً فيه.
Here's a little clip of something I think I did poorly.
أما هنا فأظن أنني كنت سيئاً.
Advise me -- when this kid acted up, how should I have dealt with that?"
انصحوني-- عندما تصرف هذا الطفل, كيف وجب علي أن أتعامل معه؟"
And they could all sit and work together on those problems.
ويمكن لهم جميعاً الجلوس سوياً لحل هذه المشاكل.
You can take the very best teachers and kind of annotate it,
كما يمكن أخذ أميز المعلمين وتسجيل أسمائهم,
have it so everyone sees who is the very best at teaching this stuff.
بحيث يتاح للجميع معرفة من هو الأميز في تدريس هذه المادة.
You can take those great courses and make them available
كذلك يمكن أخذ هذه الدورات الرائعة وتوفيرها
so that a kid could go out and watch the physics course, learn from that.
بحيث يستطيع الولد الخروج ومشاهدة مادة الفيزياء, ويتعلم منها.
If you have a kid who's behind,
فلو كان لديك ولد ضعيف,
you would know you could assign them that video to watch and review the concept.
فستعرف أنه بإمكانك أن تحدد له ذلك الفيديو ليشاهده و يراجع فكرته.
And in fact, these free courses could not only be available just on the Internet,
وفي الواقع, فإن تلك الحصص المجانية لا يُحصر توفيرها على الإنترنت فقط,
but you could make it so that DVDs were always available,
وإنما بالإمكان تجهيزها على DVD لتكون متوفرة دوماً.
and so anybody who has access to a DVD player can have the very best teachers.
وبذلك فأي شخص لديه جهاز تشغيل DVD سيتمكن من متابعة أفضل المعلمين.
And so by thinking of this as a personnel system,
ولو فكر في الموضوع عن طريق هيئة موظفين
we can do it much better.
فسنتمكن من إظهاره بشكل أفضل.
Now there's a book actually, about KIPP --
وهنا كتاب في الواقع, عن KIPP
the place that this is going on --
- المكان الذي يجري فيه كل ما سبق -
that Jay Matthews, a news reporter, wrote -- called, "Work Hard, Be Nice."
كتبه Jay Matthews, مراسل صحفي, واسماه "Work Hard, Be Nice" " أعمل بجد, تكن جميلاً "
And I thought it was so fantastic.
وأظن بأنه رائع للغاية.
It gave you a sense of what a good teacher does.
فهو يجعلك تتعرف على ما يفعله المعلم الرائع.
I'm going to send everyone here a free copy of this book.
وسأرسل لكل واحد هنا نسخة مجانية من هذا الكتاب.
(Applause)
( تصفيق )
Now, we put a lot of money into education,
إننا نضخ الكثير من المال في التعليم.
and I really think that education is the most important thing to get right
وأعتقد جازماً بأن التعليم هو أهم عامل للحصول على ما ينفع
for the country to have as strong a future as it should have.
الوطن لتمتلك مستقبلاً قوياً كما ينبغي.
In fact we have in the stimulus bill -- it's interesting --
وفي الحقيقة كان لدينا توصية - رائعة -
the House version actually had money in it for these data systems,
فنسخة مجلس النواب تضمنت مبالغ من أجل هذه الأنظمة البيانية,
and it was taken out in the Senate
لكن سحبها مجلس الشيوخ
because there are people who are threatened by these things.
لأن هناك أشخاص مهددون بها.
But I -- I'm optimistic.
ومع ذلك فإنني متفائل.
I think people are beginning to recognize how important this is,
ففي ظني أن الناس بدأت تعي مدى أهمية ذلك,
and it really can make a difference for millions of lives, if we get it right.
ويمكن أن تحدث فرقاً بالنسبة لملايين الأرواح, لو عملناها بشكل صحيح.
I only had time to frame those two problems.
لقد كان لدي وقتاً يتناسب لطرح هاتين المشكلتين.
There's a lot more problems like that --
وإلا فهناك الكثير من المشاكل مثل
AIDS, pneumonia -- I can just see you're getting excited,
- الإيدز, والإلتهاب الرئوي - ويمكنني أن أرى الإثارة التي تبدو عليكم,
just at the very name of these things.
بمجرد ذكر هذه الأمراض.
And the skill sets required to tackle these things are very broad.
والمهارات المطلوبة لمعالجة هذه الأمور واسعة جداً.
You know, the system doesn't naturally make it happen.
وكما تعلمون بأن النظام لا يساهم في إيجادها بالشكل الطبيعي.
Governments don't naturally pick these things in the right way.
فالحكومات لا تنتقي هذه الأشياء بالشكل المطلوب.
The private sector doesn't naturally put its resources into these things.
والقطاع الخاص لا يضع موارده في هذه الأمور بالطريقة المأمولة.
So it's going to take brilliant people like you
لذا هي بحاجة إلى أناس أذكياء مثلكم
to study these things, get other people involved --
ليدرسوا هذه المشاكل, ويحثوا الآخرين على ذلك
and you're helping to come up with solutions.
فأنتم ستساعدون في إيجاد الحلول.
And with that, I think there's some great things that will come out of it.
وبهذا, أظن بأن هناك بعض الأمور العظيمة التي ستنبثق منها.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)